A Guide to the Clinton H. Cowgill Collection, 1916-1977
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Clinton H. Cowgill Collection, 1916-1977
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va.
Ms1978-009
1 box and 1 oversized folder; 0.5 cu. ft.
The Clinton H. Cowgill Collection contains selected personal and professional correspondence, writing, incomplete architectural drawings, and career documentation of the founder of VPI's architecture program, Clinton Cowgill.
Mabel Cowgill
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
The Clinton H. Cowgill Collection was donated to Newman Library in 1978.
Biographical Information
In 1916, Clinton H. Cowgill (1890-1975) graduated from the University of Illinois with a degree in Architecture and later received a master's degree from the same institution. In conjunction with an independent practice, Cowgill was in charge of teaching architectural design at Iowa State College for eight years until 1928. Changing universities, Cowgill founded the architectural engineering department at VPI (now Virginia Tech) in 1928 - establishing, at the time, the only architecture program in Virginia. Serving as head of the department for 28 years, Cowgill later became the namesake of the architecture building dedicated in 1960. During his time at Tech, Cowgill designed two houses in Blacksburg which are now listed on the National Register of Historic Places. Besides teaching, Cowgill published Architecture Practice and Building for Investment and was highly involved in professional organizations. Cowgill's professional involvement is apparent in his 1950 tenure as the President of the National Council of Architecture Registration Boards (NCARB) and his designation as a fellow of the American Institute of Architects (FAIA). Cowgill acted as the editor for the AIA until his retirement in 1961. Clinton H. Cowgill spent his retirement years in La Jolla, California with his wife, Mabel, until his death in 1975.
Scope and Content
The materials in the Clinton H. Cowgill collection range from 1916 to 1977 and contain information concerning Mr. Cowgill's association with Virginia Tech (formerly VPI) and its architecture department, the founding of Cowgill Hall, Cowgill's involvement with the American Institute of Architects, the publication of Cowgill's books, and incomplete architectural drawings of a residence. The collection also contains personal documents such as a family tree, condolence letters (after Cowgill's death), and various certificates and accolades. Also included is a humorous scrapbook entitled "Handbook of Architectural Malpractice" which contains an assortment of personal photos and clippings.
Arrangement
Organized by subject, the larger sections include correspondence, photographs, and printed material (both published and non-published works).
Contents List
- Speech by E. B. Cowgill, Passengers on the 'Welcome,' and Cowgill Family Tree, 1897; n.d. (Box-folder 1:1)
- Executor Document from the Estate of Ben John Small, 1957 (Box-folder 1:2)
- Cowgill Correspondence, 1928-1977 (Box-folder 1:3)
- Mabel Cowgill Correspondence, 1975-1976 (Box-folder 1:4)
- Newspaper Clippings and Pamphlet on Cowgill Hall (Box-folder 1:5)
- Certificates and Awards, 1937-1965 (Box-folder 1:6)
- Diplomas from the University of Illinois 1916,1925 (Oversize 1)
- 12 Photographs of Buildings Designed by Cowgill (Box-folder 1:7-8)
  Airplane Hanger for VPI; Residence for L. B. Dietrich; Residence for L. C. Beamer; Residence for Miss Hallie Hughes; Residence for Geo Herring; Residence for Reese Bryant; Res. for John Whittemore, Res. for C. A. Montgomery; Residence for H.W. Sanders; Dairy Husbandry Bldg, VPI; Dairy Husbandry Bldg, VPI; University Club (previous listings in Blacksburg, VA); Highway Commission, Ames, Iowa
- Introduction to Parts 1 and 2 of Urbanization with captions (Box-folder 1:9)
- Unpublished manuscript, Urbanization, Chapters 1-9 (Box-folder 1:10-11)
- Notes on Architectural Practice by Cowgill, 1947 (Box-folder 1:12)
- Bulletin of the Virginia Polytechnic Institute, 1955 (Box-folder 1:13)
- Handbook of Architectural Malpractice (Box-folder 1:14)
- 6 Reproduction Drawings for the Residence of Prof. and Mrs. John Whittemore 1936 (Oversize 2)